Finding Aid for James Craig Watson papers, 1855-1881
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James Craig Watson papers 1855-1881
Watson, James C. (James Craig), 1838-1880.
1 oversize folders
2 linear feet
86223 Aa 2; Ac
Professor of astronomy and director of the Observatory at University of Michigan and University of Wisconsin. Correspondence, professional papers, travel journals, and files of astronomical observations and calculations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection came from Miss Agnes Alta Waite (donor no. 2556 ) in January 1949. Most of the astronomical observations and calculations came from the University of Michigan Dept. of Astronomy (donor no. 1465 ). Other materials were transferred from the U-M Graduate Library (donor no. 1278 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
James Craig Watson (January 28, 1838-November 22, 1880) was a Canadian-American astronomer born in the village of Fingal, Ontario Canada. His family relocated to Ann Arbor, Michigan in 1850. In 1857, Watson graduated from the University of Michigan where he had studied the classics, mathematics, and the principles of theoretical and practical astronomy taught by professor Franz Brünnow. After graduation, Watson worked as Brünnow's assistant, and when his mentor resigned in 1859, Watson was made professor of astronomy in charge of the Observatory. Brünnow returned in 1860, resigned again in 1863, and at this time, Watson assumed the position as second director of Detroit Observatory serving until 1879.
Watson contributed to various astronomical journals and was the author of Popular Treatise on Comets (1861) and Theoretical Astronomy (1868). Watson, in addition, made good use of the Observatory telescope. He was the discover of 22 asteroids, beginning with 79 Eurynome in 1863. One of his asteroid discoveries, 139 Juewa was made in Beijing when Watson was there to observe the 1874 transit of Venus.
Watson was a strong believer in the existence of the planet Vulcan, a hypothetical planet closer to the Sun than Mercury, which is now known not to exist (however the existence of small Vulcanoid planetoids remains a possibility). He believed he had seen two such planets during a July 1878 solar eclipse in Wyoming.
In 1879, Watson resigned his position at the University of Michigan to become director of the Washburn Observatory of the University of Wisconsin. He died November 22, 1880.
The James C. Watson collection consists of correspondence with astronomers, University of Michigan colleagues, and other scientists and inventors; professional papers, travel journals of trips to Alaska, China, Sicily, Egypt and Arabia; and files of astronomical observations and calculations, mainly pertaining to asteroids. The papers are organized into the following series: Correspondence and related; Professional papers; Travel and personal; Photographs; and Astronomical observations calculations.
Subjects:
Astronomy--United States.; China--History--1861-1912.; Egypt--Description and travel.; Piano.; Telephone.; Voyages and travels.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Detroit Observatory.; Watson, James C. (James Craig), 1838-1880.; Centennial Exhibition (1876: Philadelphia, Pa.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; Watson, Annette Waite.; Watson, James C. (James Craig), 1838-1880.
Contributors:
Bell, Alexander Graham, 1847-1922.; Chase, A. W. (Alvin Wood), 1817-1885.; Gray, Elisha, 1835-1901.; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878.; Upjohn, William E.; Vaughan, Victor C. (Victor Clarence), 1851-1929.; Watson, Annette Waite.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Prints.
- Correspondence and related
  The correspondence relates to astronomy and observatories. Among his correspondents were A.W. Chase, 1873-1874; Joseph Henry, 1877; William E. Upjohn, 1880; and Victor C. Vaughan, 1880. The correspondence concern in part Watson's participation in the piano exhibit at the 1876 Centennial Exhibition.
  - 1857-1858 (Box 1)
  - 1862-1867 (Box 1)
  - 1868 (Box 1)
  - 1869 (Box 1)
  - 1870 (Box 1)
  - 1871 (Box 1)
  - 1872 (Box 1)
  - 1873 (Box 1)
  - 1874 (Box 1)
  - 1875 (Box 1)
  - 1876 (Box 1)
  - 1877 (Box 1)
  - 1878 (Box 1)
  - 1879 (Box 1)
    (include letter of resignation of Watson as director of the Observatory and professor of astronomy, February 6, 1879)
  - 1880-1881 (Box 1)
  - Letterpress book 1858-1866 (Box 1)
  - Letterpress book 1869-1874 (Box 1)
- Professional papers
  The Professional papers series is noteworthy for its information on the dispute between Alexander Graham Bell and Elisha Gray over the invention of the telephone.
  - Alexander Graham Bell-Elisha Gray controversy over invention of first telephone 1876-1877 (Box 1)
    (include letters, patent, and other documents)
  - "On the determination of the orbits of planets and comets" paper presented to the Michigan Scientific Association June 1863 (Box 1)
  - Biographical information: include report of the faculty activities of James C. Watson 1875-1877 and biographical sketch written by Heber D. Curtis (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folder)
  - Manuscripts of writings and miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Travel and personal
  The Travel and personal series relates to the travels of Watson and his wife to China and to Egypt and Arabia, mostly to participate in astronomical observations. Here the research will also find letters of Annette Watson to family and friends describing her travels abroad, 1874-1875.
  - Notebook containing outlines of readings, list of books in his library 1858 (Box 1)
  - Travel diary to Sicily, 1870-1871 (Box 1)
  - Log on Steamship "Alaska" of voyage from San Francisco to Yokohama July 28, 1874-August 19, 1874 with navigational computations (Box 1)
  - Description of trip to Temple of Heaven 1874 (Box 1)
  - Journal of voyage to Shanghai January 19-March 27, 1875 (Box 1)
  - Travel diary of trip to Egypt and Arabia (Box 1)
  - Travel diary, 1875 probably of Mrs. Watson (Box 1)
    (in pencil)
  - Letters of Annette Watson to family and friends while traveling abroad 1874-1875 (Box 1)
  - Judge's notebook 1876 centennial exhibition (Box 1)
- Visual materials
  - Photographic portraits (Box 1)
  - Print of JCW (Box 1)
- Astronomical observations and calculations, mainly pertaining to asteroids
  - Notebook 1855 (Box 2)
    (microfilm copy available)
  - "Reduction of time observations, transit of Mercury" May 1878 (Box 2)
  - New Planet discovered at Peking, China October 10, 1874 (Box 2)
  - Eclipse of the Sun July 29, 1878 (Box 2)
  - Supposed planet between Mercury and the Sun (Box 2)
  - Optical Papers (Box 2)
  - Asteroid Discoveries
    - Helena 101 (Box 2)
    - Clymene 104 (Box 2)
    - Artemis 105 (Box 2)
    - Thyra 115 (Box 2)
    - Althaea 119 (Box 2)
    - Hermione 121 (Box 2)
    - Aethra 132 (Box 2)
    - Juewa 139 (Box 2)
    - Athor 161 (Box 2)
    - Sibylla 168 (Box 2)
    - Phaedra 174 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Charts, calculations, and Miscellaneous outsize material (Folder AC)